Guide to the Carl Woodring collection on Charles Ricketts and Charles Shannon,1846-2001, bulk 1898-1986 MS 513
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Carl Woodring collection on Charles Ricketts and Charles Shannon
1846-2001
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Woodring, Carl, 1919-2009
MS 513
5 Linear Feet (10 boxes + oversized materials)
This collection contains the Charles Ricketts and Charles Shannon research material of Dr. Carl Woodring including correspondence, articles and theses, works, Vale Press items, exhibition catalogs and other printed material. An extensive book collection, paintings and drawings are included in the collection.
Biographical Sketch
Carl Woodring (1919-) was born in Texas, received his B.A. from Rice University in Houston and his M.A. and Ph.D. from Harvard. Dr. Woodring, Woodberry Professor Emeritus of Literature, Columbia University, has been accorded many distinctions including the Phi Beta Kappa award (1972) for his book on William Wordsworth, Politics in English Romantic Poetry, a Ford Foundation grant for 1955-56 and a Guggenheim Fellowship for 1958-59. Considered a renowned authority on the Romantic Period in English Literature, Woodring is the author of numerous articles and books including Politics in the Poetry of Coleridge (1961), Wordsworth (1965),Nature into Art: Cultural Transformations in Nineteenth-Century Britain (1989), (ed.) Table Talk of Samuel Taylor Coleridge for the Collected Coleridge, 2 vols. (1990), and (ed.) The Columbia History of British Poetry (1994).
Charles de Sousy Ricketts was born in Geneva, Switzerland on October 2, 1866. He was known as a book designer, theatre designer, sculptor and painter. His mother was musical; his father a painter of marine subjects. Ricketts spent his early years in Lausanne and London and his youth at Boulogne and Amiens in France. After his mother's death, he returned to London with his father and in 1882 entered the City and Guilds Art School in Kennington, London, where he was apprenticed to Charles Roberts, a prominent wood-engraver. His father died a year later and on his sixteenth birthday he met his lifelong partner, Charles Haselwood Shannon.
Ricketts and Shannon founded an occasional art journal, The Dial (1889-1897) and the two artists also began designing and illustrating books, including Daphnis and Chloe (1893) and Hero and Leander (1894). Ricketts also worked for commercial publishers; his more famous books include John Gray's Silverpoints (1893) and Oscar Wilde's The Sphinx (1895).
In 1894 Ricketts met Llewellyn Hacon, a wealthy barrister, enabling him to realize his dream of being a publisher and he set up the Vale Press (1896-1904). Ricketts designed three fonts and numerous decorations and illustrations. After the closing of the Vale Press in 1904, he designed books for friends such as Katherine Bradley (1946-1914) and Edith Cooper (1862-1913) (pseudonym Michael Field) and Gordon Bottomley (1874-1948).
In 1900, Ricketts took up painting and sculpture. He was elected Associate of the Royal Academy in 1922 and Royal Academician in 1928. Ricketts also produced theatrical designs and was involved in about forty productions, including George Bernard Shaw's St. Joan. He wrote several books on art and other subjects and acted as art consultant to various individuals and institutions
He and Shannon also built up their own collection of paintings, drawings, and antiquities; many are now at the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge and at the British Museum. Charles Shannon, falling from a ladder, became disabled; this devastated Ricketts who died of a heart attack in 1931 – six years before his friend.
Charles Haselwood Shannon was born in Lincolnshire on April 26, 1863. He attended St. John's School, Leatherhead (1873-1881) and then studied at the City and Guilds Technical Art School, an extension of the Lambeth Art School (1881-1885). It was there he met Charles Ricketts and it was the start of a lifelong friendship. By 1888, they had devised a strategy for their joint career; Ricketts was to provide the income and Shannon perfected his abilities as a painter. In 1897, Shannon sent two paintings and some lithographs to Munich where he was awarded a gold medal. Shannon's self-portrait, The Man in the Black Shirt was completed that year.
Ricketts was the dominant figure in the artistic and literary circle that formed around them in Chelsea (1888-1898) and then in Richmond (1898-1902). Joint activities included their magazine, The Dial (1889-1897), design and illustration of Oscar Wilde's books and wood-engravings for editions of Daphnis and Chloe (1893) and Hero and Leander (1894). They set up the Vale Press in 1896 complemented with a shop where work by Shannon and their friends could be bought.
Shannon had his own lithographic press and he produced a number of works including A Lithograph in White Line (1891), Summer (1892), and The Shepherd in a Mist. In painting, his traditional technique, deriving from the Venetians and the English eighteenth century, were the bases of his art. His works include an early success, The Lady with a Cyclamen (1899), a favorite sitter, Kathleen Bruce (1878-1947), is seen as The Sculptress (1904) and in The Winged Hat.
In 1902 Ricketts and Shannon returned to London to live in a flat in a block in Lansdowne Road, Holland Park. Shannon became an active exhibitor, for example at the New English Art Club and the International Society. He was elected Associate of the Royal Academy in 1911 and Royal Academician in 1920.
In January 1929 Shannon suffered a fall while hanging a picture in Townshend House, Regents Park, where they had moved in 1923. He suffered brain damage and never fully recovered. Ricketts sold some works to pay for nursing expenses and more went after Rickett's death in 1931. Charles Shannon died on March 18, 1937.
Excerpted from the Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, 2006.
Scope and Contents
The materials are comprised of correspondence from Dr. Woodring to other Ricketts and Shannon scholars, booksellers, museums and libraries. There is also correspondence from Ricketts and Shannon as well as those in their circle such as Laurence Binyon, Gordon Bottomley and Thomas Sturge Moore.
Biographical material such as theses, articles, essays and exhibition catalogs are included as well as photocopies of artwork by Ricketts and Shannon. Included are proofs such as "The Sleeping Methymnaeans," signed by Shannon, from Daphnis and Chloe. Charles Ricketts and Charles Shannon both worked on the designs and the cutting of the wood-blocks for this Vale Press publication. Of special note are works of art by Ricketts and Shannon, including oil paintings, drawings and a large collection of Shannon's lithographs.
Vale Press ephemera, such as notices, prospectuses, and invitations are included. A collection of Vale Press titles, including The Vale Shakespeare (1900-1904), as well as an extensive book collection on Ricketts and Shannon, are among the holdings.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Provenance
This collection was a gift donated by Carl Woodring in 2004.
Related Materials
The Ricketts and Shannon Book Collection, a cataloged book collection on Ricketts and Shannon, British cultural history, wood engraving, book illustration, theater design, notables such as Oscar Wilde, W.B. Yeats and Laurence Binyon, and of special note, a collection of Vale Press titles.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following eight series:
Missing Title
Series I: Biographical information including theses, articles, and catalogs, 1914-1979
Series II: Personal and business correspondence, Carl Woodring, 1951- 2000
Series III: Correspondence, Charles Ricketts and Charles Shannon, 1904-1931
Series IV: Other correspondents, Ricketts and Shannon contemporaries and others, 1846-1946
Series V: Designs and works, Charles Ricketts and Charles Shannon, and others, 1821-1999
Series VI: Paintings and drawings, framed and oversized, 1890-1925
Series VII: Exhibition and auction catalogs, 1895-1997, undated
Series VIII: Card files, circa 1965 - 2002
Index Terms
Subjects
Illustration of books -- Great Britain; Graphic design (Typography); Art
Document Types
paintings (visual works); exhibition catalogs; lithographs; corrrespondence; drawings (visual works)
Subjects (Persons)
Binyon, Laurence, 1869-1943; Bottomley, Gordon, 1874-1948; Bradley, Katharine Harris, 1846-1914; Cockerell, Sydney Carlyle, Sir, 1867-1962; Masefield, John, 1878-1967; Le Gallienne, Richard, 1866-1947; Ricketts, Charles S., 1886-1931; Moore, T. Sturge (Thomas Sturge), 1870-1944; Delaney, Paul, 1948-; Cooper, Edith Emma, 1862-1913; Hutchinson, F. E. (Francis Ernest), 1871-1947; Hacon, W. Llewellyn (William Llewellyn), 1860-1910; Woodring, Carl, 1919-2009; Shannon, Charles Hazelwood, 1863-1937; Rothenstein, William, 1872-1945
Subjects (Corporations)
Ballantyne Press.; Vale Press.
- Series I: Biographical information including theses, articles, and catalogs, 1914-1979; 238733
  - Thesis, The Artistic Theories of Charles Ricketts, and their Application in His Book Illustration, by Alan Fern, 1954, 238742 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Thesis, A Critical Examination of the Theatrical Designs of Charles Ricketts, by Eric Binnie, 1978, 238741 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gordon Bottomley, Grolier Club articles on Charles Ricketts, 1932, 1982, 238740 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carl Woodring biography proposal on Charles Shannon and Charles Ricketts, 1979, 238739 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wills and bequests, 1917, 1929, 238738 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Catalog listing of Ricketts and Shannon personal collection, 1933, 238737 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Catalogs, Ricketts and Shannon exhibitions with biographical information on Charles Ricketts, 1914, 1966, 238736 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Charles Shannon article, by Paul Delaney, 1979, 238735 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, articles, catalog notices, 1895-1970, 238734 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Personal and business correspondence, Carl Woodring, 1951- 2000, 238717; This series includes incoming and outgoing correspondence of Carl Woodring with the following correspondents.
  - Stephen Calloway, 1980, 1982, 238732 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - E.E. Cummings, 1951, 238731 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Paul Delaney, 1978-1988, 238730 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Charles Gullesin, 1966-1982, 238729 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Laurence Irving, 1972-1985, 238728 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ian Kenyur Hodgkins, 1979, 238727 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - James Nelson, 1967, 1969, 238726 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Albert Sperisen, 1971-1982, 238725 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Riette Sturge Moore, 1971-1986, undated, 238724 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Paul van Capleeven, 1997-1998, 238723 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bertram Rota, Ltd. (Anthony Rota, bookseller), 1968-2000, 238722 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bookseller correspondence, 1964-1990, 238721 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bookseller correspondence (want lists), undated, 238720 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Museum and library correspondence, 1965-1990, 238719 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, other correspondents, 1965-1990, 238718 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series III: Correspondence, Charles Ricketts and Charles Shannon, 1904-1931, 238714
  - Charles Ricketts correspondence, 1906-1931, 238716 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    General note
    to Monsieur Douvray, of Anglo-French Review, postcard, undated
    to James Louis Garvin, [1917]
    to Mr. Laing regarding the book Titian, seven letters, 1906 –1910
    to J.A. Wilson regarding recollections of Oscar Wilde, [July 1931] and postcard, July 14, 1931
    to Howes Norris, Jr. (for autograph collection), November 9, 1930
    to Dear Sir, a note card, …Shannon is too ill to send you his autograph, undated
  - Charles Shannon correspondence, 1904-1929, 238715 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    to Dear Sir, a reply with prices for four of his paintings, July 11, 1904
    to Dear Sir, Pennel is wrong as usual…, April 11, 1911
    to Mr. Bramley, for autograph collection, December 17, 1929
- Series IV: Other Correspondents, Ricketts and Shannon contemporaries and others, 1846-1946, 238696
  - Laurence Binyon correspondence, 1918-1932, 238713 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    to Sir John Adcock, ed. Bookman, June 21, 1918, October 21, 1921 and January 4, 1925
    to Miss Dawson, December 29, 1928
    to Francis Hutchinson, June 17, 1930
    to Sydney Matthwan, January 22, 1925
    to Wilson, September 19, 1932
  - Gordon Bottomley correspondence, 1925-1946, 238712 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    to Clara T. Huttenbach, March 29, 1928 and August 8, 1930
    to Graham Huttenbach (a verse), February 17, 1925
    to Lillah McCarthy (Lady Keeble), December 27, 1941
    to Charles Ricketts, May 11, 1929
    to Graham Robertson, April 12, 1933
    to Jacques Vallette, June 3, 1946
  - Mary Cholmondeley to Lady Isabel November 27, [1902] and note, No, no wicked temptress…, November 28 [1902], 238711 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sydney C. Cockerell to Cormell Price, December 23, 1909, 238710 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Thomas Evelyn Ellis to Mrs. Balkwill, October 16, 1922, 238709 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Richard le Gallienne to Van der Weyde, undated, 238708 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ryllis Hacon (photograph of Mrs. Llewelyn Hacon inscribed to William Rothenstein), 1899, 238707 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Anna Mary Howett to [William] Hepworth Dixon, [1856], 238706 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Mary Howett and William Howett correspondence, circa 1845-1861, 238705 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    From Mary to Anna (Botham) Harrison (Mary's sister), [Spring, 1846]
    From Mary to John Chapman, April 26, 1853
    From Mary to R.H. Mason, March 6
    From Mary to Dear Sir [Woods], March 28, [1861]
    From William to Gentlemen regarding Bremer's Life in Delecarlia, circa 1845
    From William to Marcus Spring, March 28, 1861
  - George Herbert Leigh Mallory to Francis Hutchinson, undated, 238704 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Also a manuscript card, with poem In memoriam to Mallory and Irvine, who lost their lives in the Mount Everest Expedition, 1924. Found in Hutchinson's copy of Laurence Binyon, The Sirens: an Ode, 1925
  - John Edward Masefield (publicity photograph), 1916, 238703 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Joseph Pennell to Gleeson White, undated, 238702 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lennox Robinson correspondence, 1933,1946, undated, 238701 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    to R. B. Marriott, 1933
    Postcard to Hubert Burgess, 1946
    Abbey Theatre announcement and photograph of cat, signed on verso of mount, undated
  - James Jebsua Shannon to Dear Madam…, 1890, 238700 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Thomas Sturge Moore to Walter M. Sinclair, 1905, 238699 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - John Addington Symonds to Sir Henry Layard, 1883, 238698 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Mary Seton Watts to Cecil French, 1928, 238697 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Series V: Designs and works, Charles Ricketts and Charles Shannon, and others, 1821-1999, 238673
  - Charles Ricketts, proofs, 1899, 1903, undated, 238695 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Copeland & Day, proof of bookplate. Line block in black on thin Japanese paper, undated
    De Cupidinis et Psyches Amoribus, India paper, proof 1, signed in pencil, Vale, 1901
    The Parables from the Gospels (The Lost Piece of Silver), India paper, proof 5, signed in pencil, Vale, 1903
    A Defense of the Revival of Printing, p. 3-6 on vellum, border and design by Ricketts, Vale, 1899
    Une Messe Macabre, India paper, engraved by Ricketts after Legros, signed A. Legros, undated
    Young Girl and Death, India paper, engraved by Ricketts after Legros, signed A. Legros, undated
    Oscar Wilde, Poems, proof of endpapers, 1892
  - Shannon proofs, 1893, 238694 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Daphnis and Chloe (Love in a Dream), India paper, trial proof, signed C. Shannon, 1893
  - Galley proofs, page proofs for Michael Field, by Charles Ricketts, edited by Paul Delaney, 1976, 238693 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Galley proofs, page proofs for Some Letters from Charles Ricketts and Charles Shannon to Michael Field, edited by Paul Delaney, 1979, 238692 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Charles Ricketts essay (photocopy, 2001), 1st printing, 1899, 238691 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Art works (photocopies) of Ricketts and Shannon, circa 1896-1930, 238690 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bookjackets (Ricketts designs), undated, 238689 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Vale Press ephemera, circa 1896-1899, 238688 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    The list of books to be published by Messrs. Hacon & Ricketts at The Sign of the Dial… circa 1898 (2 copies)
    A List of Books Issued by Messrs. Halcon & Ricketts at the Sign of the Dial…, 1898
    The First Exhibition of Original Engraving. The Dutch Gallery, 1898
    A List of Books Issued by Messrs. Hacon & Ricketts, The Vale Press, 1899
    The Tragedy of Hamlet, Prince of Denmark, 1899
  - Vale Press ephemera, circa 1900-1903, 238687 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Famous Woodcuts Illustrations of the Fifteenth and Early Sixteenth Centuries, circa 1900
    The Woodcut Illustrations of Millais, circa 1900
    Notice, in offering the following books…, circa 1900
    A List of Vale Press Books Issued by Hacon & Ricketts… The Printing numbers given include all French and American editions, all presentation copies, and all copied destroyed in the fire of December 1899, circa 1900
    Special Notice The 'Avon' fount of small pica type, upon which Mr. Ricketts has long been engaged…, circa 1900
    Orders for bindings in pigskin and morocco can now be…, circa 1900
    The following two books will be issued during the autumn of 1900… Poems of Alfred Lloyd Tennyson, circa 1900
    Special Notice. Arrangements have now been made for the completion of the Vale Shakespeare before the end of June 1903, when the firm of Hacon & Ricketts will cease publishing, and the Avon and Vale founts will be destroyed, January, 1903
    Final list of books to be issued…, circa 1903
    Bibliography of the Vale Press, Vale type in red, circa 1904
  - Vale Press prospectuses, circa 1896-1903, 238686; Prospectuses for a number of publications including Poems of Alfred Lloyd Tennyson, The Rowley Poems of Thomas Chatterton, and others. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Items printed by the Vale Press, 1899, 1904, 238685 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Messrs. Hacon & Ricketts beg to announce that on September 7th, 1899, they are moving…, circa 1899
    …having no retail business, cannot supply orders from "those with whom they have no accounts…, circa 1899
    Messrs. Hacon & Rickett's TRADE TERMS in future will be 20 percent…, circa 1899
    Invitation, folded, Mr. E. J. Van Wisselingh requests the pleasure…private view of an exhibition of drawings, pastels, lithographs and woodcuts by Charles Shannon, circa 1899
    Photographs of early type designs…, Woolley, September, 1904
    Proof of Hacon & Ricketts mailing label, with penciled instructions for change, possibly by C. J. Holmes, 1899
  - Articles on the Vale Press and English book illustration, 1900, 1903, 238684 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Listing of Vale Press publications, 1896-1903, 238683 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Charles Ricketts theatrical sketches (photocopies), 1906-1922, 238682 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Theater programs, designs, 1889-1938, 238681 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Theater programs, designs, 1950-1985, undated, 238680 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Johns Masefield's Mystery Play, The Coming of Christ in Graphic: The National Weekly (photocopy), May 26, 1928, 238679 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Articles, reviews and catalogs, 1891-1935, 238678 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Articles, reviews and catalogs, 1940-2001, 238677 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Catalogs (photocopies) of Ricketts and Shannon exhibitions, 1909, 1933, 1963, 238676 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Articles and catalogs on Shannon's lithographs, 1897,1920, 1938, 238675 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Works by others (reproductions), 1821-1950, undated, 238674 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series VI: Paintings and Drawings, framed and oversized, 1890-1925, 238622
  - Charles Ricketts, paintings and watercolor, 1901-1925, 238662
    - The Good Samaritan, oil sketch on panel board, framed, 1901, 238672
    - The Samaritan at the Inn Door, oil on canvas, framed, 1901, 238671
    - Nessus and Dejanira, oil on canvas, framed., 238670
    - Oil on canvas, unsigned, framed, 1901, 238669
    - The Descent from the Cross, oil on canvas, framed, 1905, 238668
    - Costume design for Judith, watercolor on wove paper, framed, 1916, 238667 (Frame WRC staff office 160B)
    - Stage design [for Judith], gouache, framed [1916], 238666 (Frame WRC staff office 160B)
    - Costume design for the Cecil Lewis operetta Montezuma, watercolor on wove paper, framed, circa 1925, 238665
    - Figures in a landscape, partly stripped from board P4519, oil on board, framed, 238664
    - Pieta, oil on canvas, framed, 238663
  - Charles Shannon, lithographs and woodcuts, 1890 -1920, 238632
    - The Sleeping Methymneans, proof in brown, 1893, 238656 (Drawer 103, Item 1)
    - The Porch, woodcut, circa 1890, 238661 (Drawer 103, Item 2)
    - Coral Divers, woodcut, circa 1890, 238660 (Drawer 103, Item 2)
    - Autumn, woodcut, circa 1890, 238659 (Drawer 103, Item 2)
    - The Snow-Winter, lithograph (a fan), 1907, 238637 (Drawer 103, Item 3)
    - The Promontory, lithograph (a fan), 1907, 238638 (Drawer 103, Item 4)
    - The Three Sisters, lithograph, 1894, 238650 (Drawer 103, Item 5)
    - The Toilet, lithograph, 1895, 238646 (Drawer 103, Item 6)
    - W. L. Hacon, Esq., lithograph, 1896, 238645 (Drawer 103, Item 7)
    - Alphonse Legros, lithograph, 1896, 238644 (Drawer 103, Item 8)
    - Max Beerbohm, lithograph, 1896, 238643 (Drawer 103, Item 9)
    - An Idyll, color lithograph, 1905, 238641 (Drawer 103, Item 10)
    - Autumn, lithograph, 1917, 238635 (Drawer 103, Item 11)
    - The Ebb Tide, lithograph, 1917, 238634 (Drawer 103, Item 12)
    - The Tidal River, lithograph, 1920, 238633 (Drawer 103, Item 13)
    - E. J. Van Wissenlingh, lithograph, 1895, 238649 (Drawer 103)
    - Morning, color lithograph, 1905, 238640 (Drawer 103)
    - The Fantastic Dress, lithograph, 1890, 238658 (Box 11)
    - Atalanta, lithograph, 1893, 238657 (Box 11)
    - Biondina, lithograph, reverse of The Fantastic Dress, 1894, 238655 (Box 11)
    - Shell- Gatherers, lithograph, 1894, 238654 (Box 11)
    - Linen Bleachers, lithograph, 1894, 238653 (Box 11)
    - The Messenger, lithograph, 1894, 238652 (Box 11)
    - Sea and Breeze, lithograph, 1894, 238651 (Box 11)
    - The Letter, transfer lithograph, 1895, 238648 (Box 11)
    - The Dive, transfer lithograph, 1895, 238647 (Box 11)
    - The Wall Cupboard, transfer lithograph, 1897, 238642 (Box 11)
    - Portrait of the Artist, lithograph, 1905, 238639 (Box 11)
    - Sea Coast, lithograph, 1908, 238636 (Box 11)
    - Mother and Child, lithograph (Box 11)
    - The Pursuit (Box 11)
    - Repeated Bend, transfer lithograph, 1892 (Box 11)
    - The Intruder, 1892 (Box 11)
  - Charles Shannon, paintings and drawings, 1900-1925, 238626
    - Reflection, pencil drawing on paper, circa 1900, 238631 (Drawer 103, Item 14)
    - The Lady in Black (Miss Hilda Moore), oil on canvas, framed, 1918, 238630 (Frame WRC staff office 160C)
    - The Wounded Amazon, sanguine and white chalk on paper, circa 1922, 238629 (Box 11)
    - Ernest Law, colored chalks and pencil on paper, 1925, 238628 (Drawer 103, Item 15)
    - Return of the prodigal son, oil on canvas, framed, 1887; 238627 (Frame WRC staff office 160B)
    - The Breakwater, Charles Shannon. Oil on canvas, framed., 1904 (Frame WRC staff office 161B)
  - William Rothenstein, lithographs, 1897, 238623
    - Ricketts and Shannon, lithograph, 1897, 238625 (Box 11)
    - Charles Shannon, lithograph, 1897, 238624 (Box 11)